Quite a few of you will know who Ed
Lawrence is.
He's the chap that wears the cool glasses.
He's one of my biggest mentors in the
content creation space.
I'd even say he's a good friend.
But 14 hours ago, he uploaded a video,
and I think we could have a problem.
Let's listen to it.
And the lie is that short-form
is faster and easier to
make than long-form YouTube videos.
But let me just show you why that's
complete nonsense.
So here I've got these two glasses,
one for YouTube
and one for short-form.
And then I've got these M&M's.
And every M&M represents one task you have
to do
to get a result.
So let's start with YouTube.
Now, I recommend
that businesses post four videos a month
to YouTube.
So in terms of tasks to complete,
that is four hooks,
four scripts,
then we've got to make four thumbnails,
then we're going to shoot them all in one
batch, then we're going to edit them.
So let's edit four videos.
Then we're going to post them,
and we're going to
track four videos' results.
And that's
kind of it.
But now let's compare it to the work you
have to put in
to get short-form to work for you.
So a lot of the advice you're going to see
online about how to grow on these
platforms is going to tell you to post one
piece
of content every day. So
that means you need to come up with 30
ideas,
which is without doubt the hardest part of
this all.
Then 30 hooks,
then 30 scripts.
But then we're going to have to do 30
edits.
And this is where it gets really
time-consuming because the advice you
are given is
to post short-form videos across multiple
platforms.
So what that means
is we then have to upload 90
pieces of content,
and then we need to write
90 descriptions to go below those videos,
because that's how
short-form videos work now.
Everyone's reading the description below,
not watching
the video.
And then we need to track the performance
of
90 different pieces of content
and reply to 90 different
places where dirty little trolls
are going to send us horrible things.
Look at this.
So whoever managed to convince the world
that short-form was easier
must have been called Mark Zuckerberg,
because clearly that is a
lie.
Ed is right about a lot of what he says,
but I feel he's missing quite a bit of
nuance from the table,
and it's important you get the full story.
I've amassed over half a million YouTube
subscribers, ironically, solely through
the purpose of working with Ed. However,
short-form content has changed my
life, my businesses,
and I became a "Sunday Times" number one
bestselling author
three times just with short-form content.
I actually sold out the Hammersmith
Apollo, 3,500 people, just with short-form
content.
So I want you to absolutely go away
and watch Ed's video.
I'll put a link to it in the description.
But there's some things
that you need to think about first.
Ed is completely correct saying that
if you post four times a month,
there's a lot
less M&M's in that jar.
But what's crucial in the onset of content
creation is
feedback. Feedback from videos
that do well, feedback from videos
that don't do
well.
So if we were to create a jar of M&M's,
the sole purpose of which was to give
us feedback from what we trialed in
that video,
you would only get four M&M's back
a month versus 30
that you would get from doing short-form
content.
Ed talks about only creating four hooks,
four setups, four ideas.
But the majority of your ideas, hooks,
and setups in content are shite.
Volume is such a key component to growth
on social
media.
And I'm not talking about social media,
I'm not talking about your
followers,
I'm not talking about subscribers,
I'm talking about you.
The growth is you, how you speak,
how you present yourself, your pacing,
your
cadence, how you edit,
even becoming comfortable talking to
camera.
I would much rather you did
that 30 times a month than four.
Because if on a Monday you put half an
hour into a piece of content and it bombs,
on Tuesday you can start fresh.
If you put a week into creating a video
and it
bombs, that's a week of low confidence,
potentially low mood, low
motivation. And for me,
I'm a very impulsive person.
Ed, in his video,
talks about how he strategizes
and plans and whatever.
I watched his video.
On the way back from Sydney just now,
I drove past my house
to the studio to film this video off the
flight with no planning, no strategy.
I have a rough idea of my thumbnail,
and I think an analogy that sums this up
really well would be what Alex Hormozi
said on Chris's podcast, and I'll show you
the clip here.
Have you heard the story of the pottery
class?
There's a teacher,
and he's got two classes that he teaches.
And one class he says,
"The only assignment for this whole
semester is that you
come back with the perfect clay pot.
That's it.
That's the assignment." The other class he
says, "Your objective is to make the
most total quantity of clay pots,
and you'll be measured by how many pots
you
make." And at the end of the quarter,
the pots that came from the team that
had to just make sheer volume,
not only did they make more pots,
but the quality of
all of their pots
was better compared to the teams
that only had to make one.
And it just underlines the biggest lesson
that I've learned in my life, which is
that volume negates luck.
You can try to be lucky
and pick the one perfect
thing and try and make it, but
if you don't want to try and be lucky,
you can just
do so much fucking work
that you will brute force your way to
figuring it out.
Instead of seeing it as YouTube versus
short-form content, let's look at both of
these as tools to utilize
when developing a personal brand.
If you are putting more than 45 minutes
into a reel, I think you're putting too
much effort into it for a start.
But rather than looking at this as
something that
just gets you clients,
let's look at short-form content as
something that gets you
reps. Because early on in my journey,
posting every day was what, who made
me, me on social media. It
was the reel that I put a little bit too
much swearing
in that performed better
that made me swear in content.
There was the one time
that I drank too much caffeine before
recording a reel, and
it did a bit better.
So I mixed a lot of caffeine and swearing,
and I had my first
outlier.
The 27-year-old version of me that
was in the PT changing room
making reels between clients,
if you'd given me the task of creating
YouTube
videos, you would've overwhelmed me.
And if you'd asked me to make four YouTube
videos and they all did pretty average,
which they would,
I would've just stopped Now, Ed
and my business model could be a
little bit different.
But think about this,
the majority of people that are perfect
to work with me already have businesses
that pay the bills, whether you're a
physio, lawyer, accountant,
personal trainer.
My approach is more migrating you to 10%
of your business is online, then
20%, then 30%, then 40%.
And in some cases, that could take weeks,
in some cases,
that could take months.
The perfect step from in-person business
to me is
short-form content.
Then I would get you onto YouTube.
But I would send a very confident version
of you that's made hundreds of videos,
that's eaten a lot of shit,
that's had a lot of outliers,
that's had a lot of
repetitions of using Premiere Pro,
DaVinci, CapCut, whatever it is.
Then stage three would be sending you to
YouTube.
And I would agree with all of Ed's points
about the people on YouTube being better.
Thus,
why I'm making this video on YouTube right
now.
But let me show you something.
If we go into my YouTube Studio,
go to analytics,
and let's go to all time. £100,000.
Who's got that?
I haven't. So you'll notice down here,
2017, I created a
YouTube account. I tried growing on here,
and there was a few hundred followers
here and there,
and it slowly grew over time.
Keep in mind,
I posted my first thing on social media in
2014.
Nothing really takes off here till 2022.
So you've got to ask yourself,
why did it take you eight years to start
growing on
YouTube? And the answer is,
I wasn't man enough.
I wasn't organized enough.
I didn't understand YouTube well enough.
I couldn't even afford a camera for the
first few years.
I didn't know how to edit.
I was too busy doing personal training
sessions.
I think going from step one to step three
for most people is too big a
step.
If it wasn't for all of those videos
that I created in 15 minutes and
turned around in 30 minutes,
my brand wouldn't have been in a position
to even
start a YouTube channel
or have the luxury of building a studio.
I wouldn't have got that video
that LADbible did a piece on me to go
viral.
So much content over the years for me
was reactive.
I didn't have a chance to plan it
and strategize it and pick thumbnails.
I had to see a news article drop in the
morning.
The UK went to sleep,
and I'd have an edit ready in the
afternoon.
It was the ability to turn around an edit
in a day that made me who I am and helped
me achieve what I've achieved.
Short-form content taught me to speak to
camera.
And I'm not patient enough. Even now,
I don't put out one video a week because I
am here making as many pots as I can.
And guess what?
Even now, 12 years into content,
I still have to go here
and look at my best videos
to get an idea of what's actually working
on my channel.
I do the same on the other one. To me,
volume is such a key player in improving
competence. The same way that
if you wanted to get good at jujitsu,
I'd say go
every day. You might say,
"I'm really sore." I'd go,
"Go train in sore, because
you're going to develop a game for being
sore.
You're going to have to learn how to get
good when you're tired." Some of you out
there should be using short-form content,
not because it's the most effective, not
because the audience is good,
not because you're going to get more
clients from
there.
Because it is a great place to get daily
repetitions.
Even in the fitness industry,
the reason that we set someone 10,000
steps a day is
we have to give them something they can do
every day.
Because that's how you truly get in the
mindset of becoming about your fitness
journey. The same way
that creating content every day puts you
in the mindset of
switching into content creation.
You should be reactive.
You should be spotting trends.
You should be able to just talk to your
phone.
I don't think enough people
are just pressing the plus button on their
phones and
just talking,
just updating the world about what it
is that you do.
We've also overlooked stories.
I've had sometimes over
250,000 people watch my stories.
That's like me stood in the biggest
stadium
in the world in front of all of those
people.
And although they're watching me do random
shit like walking the dog or whatever,
it's part of my brand to build with those
people.
And another thing we're overlooking as
well here is the amount of impact that we
can get from things like carousel posts,
the integration of chatbots.
And I know I could be taking a little bit
of Ed's argument and making it my own,
but for so many of you,
short-form content
is going to make you the creator you
need to be on YouTube so that
when you hit your first video,
you're confident.
You know what to look in the viewfinder to
know that your audio's on.
You have an SD card. You know how to edit.
It's like preseason for the big leagues.
The moment I was man enough to go to
YouTube, I went to YouTube.
I love YouTube. But for me,
as a disorganized,
ADHD-brained, blithering idiot,
short-form content was easy.
I never wanted to have a big social media
account. I just wanted clients.
And I just think that
if you'd stuck me into YouTube earlier,
I would've got
overwhelmed and quit,
and I wouldn't have done the things I did,
and I wouldn't
have gone on the path I've been down.
Maybe I'm just saying this because I sell
a short-form content mastery course.
But one of the best principles I can teach
you from being a personal trainer for
all those years is progressive overload.
Some of you are just not good enough at
creating content yet to go to YouTube.
And let me tell you this, YouTube
is stressful. It's depressing.
You care about it more.
You have to put more into it.
It's a beast.
And short-form for me
was very manageable on my own.
To survive on YouTube,
I had to hire a team. Stage one,
get good at something.
Acquire skills in a domain
that you enjoy or you're good at.
Stage two,
post a lot of short-form content.
Get comfortable on camera.
Learn how to edit.
Learn how to speak to camera.
Build confidence. Stage three,
migrate to YouTube when you're a bigger,
better creator. For me, that took years.
Eight years.
Don't wait as long as I took.
Pretty much what I'm saying
is click the link in the
description.
Buy my short-form content mastery course.
Then when you finish that,
you've got your rep Sunday belt,
you might just qualify
to join Ed's course.
I suppose I'm protective over short-form
content because of
what it's done for me in my life.
Season one of my career
was all Instagram and
Facebook. I would create one reel,
put it in three places.
Sometimes Facebook would go viral,
sometimes TikTok, sometimes Instagram.
And chapter two of my life
is heavily on YouTube.
I'm grateful for both stages.
And although I agree with Ed,
I think YouTube's much better.
I just don't think some of you
are there yet. I say
that from a place of love.
I've eaten shit on YouTube enough times.
If you don't know who Ed is,
I'll put a link to his page in the
description.
Like I say,
he's changed my life for the better.
And if you're not interested in that,
YouTube recommends
that you should watch this
video here.
Says if you're a smart bugger,
you'll enjoy this one. All right. Bye-bye.